♪ ♪
Hey, what are you doing?
None of your business!
You remember me?
You were looking for
Eddie. Yeah, and you're
the guy who led me
down the primrose path.
This time you're going to talk.
That paper's five days old.
So who's going to notice?
That guy over there might.
Hi.
What the hell do
you think you're doing
running like that?
I had to. My gun was
used to shoot Joseph Chan.
The police would've
thought I did it.
They still think you did it.
Yeah, but at least
this way, I'm not in jail.
Now I know who stole the gun.
I know who shot
Mr. Chan and probably
killed the mayor.
Is there a name?
Eddie Lomax.
He flew by charter
plane to a little
hick town in Texas this morning.
How'd you find out?
I went to his hotel.
I gave the desk clerk a twenty
to let me, uh, look
at his phone bill.
Oh, good.
Now, maybe you
better turn yourself in.
I'm going to Texas.
No, no, you're not.
I have to.
You're a fugitive.
Every policeman in this
town is looking for you.
I need some cash.
Forget it! Oh, forget it.
I'm not helping you
flee across state lines.
I'm not fleeing. Forget it!
I know what I'm doing.
I'll do it if I have to walk.
Given any thought to
what you're going to do
when you find this fella?
Call you.
The police have
probably questioned
everybody around here who
has a view of Chan's house.
Oh, they think Paul
O'Neill's their man.
They're not going to ask
him any questions though.
Blow their case.
Well, I am.
Nobody's going to railroad him,
if I can help it.
He likes you, too.
I know.
I think he's got a crush on you.
How do you know?
I just know.
The way he looks at you?
Yeah. Yeah.
Hey, look.
Nobody knows what
goes on in a neighborhood
better than somebody
who never leaves it.
Mrs. Luzinsky.
Thank you so much.
You're such a dear.
You're welcome.
This smells wonderful! Good.
Thank you.
Hello.
My name is Ben Matlock
and this is Michelle Thomas.
I wonder if we might
ask you a few questions?
Why, certainly!
Come on right in.
There we are. Just
come right in there.
Oh, thank you.
Please, sit down.
Thank you. Okay.
My name is Sarah Luzinsky.
Good day.
Please, eat your
dinner while it's hot.
Oh, thank you.
Are you a police
officer too, dear?
Uh, no, no, I'm an attorney.
We're both attorneys.
You know that the man
across the street was murdered
last night? I know.
Terrible! A terrible thing!
And Mr. Chan, such a sweet man.
The yard look always so nice.
Of course, he had a gardener.
Nice-looking young man.
Very strong.
Very particular.
Pruning all the time.
Well, did you, uh, did
you notice anything...
out of the ordinary last night?
You do... spend
a... a good bit of time
in front of that window.
That's why you thought
we were police officers.
You saw me go in
Mr. Chan's house with them
last night, didn't you?
Yes.
What else did you see?
Maybe if I would have
some time to think about it.
Mrs. Luzinsky, it's all right
to get involved.
But that's not
what I'm afraid of.
If anybody, for one second...
thought you were in danger,
you'd be protected.
You mean people
will stay with me?
Sarah, you tell us what you saw,
I guarantee people
will stay with you,
talk with you, visit with you.
Well, first, I saw
a kind of tall man
with long, brown hair,
wearing cowboy boots.
He went into Mr. Chan's house.
Then, a little bit later,
another man I didn't
know went in. Uh, this man
with the long, brown
hair and cowboy boots,
did you get a good
look at his face?
Yup.
Look.
See?
Oh...
Why, look at that!
He looks just like
Lee Arthur Greenway.
Oh? I dated him once.
Oh, Lee Arthur?
Yes, when I was in high school.
- Oh...
How's it going?
Oh, well, fine,
Sergeant; thank you.
And this one looks
like Floyd Dinkleman.
Floyd Dinkleman went
to my high school, too.
He threw up a lot.
Oh... Oh, yeah, here.
Yes, sir?
What the hell is
taking her so long?
Well, she doesn't get out much
and it's kind of
fun for her to...
You kill me.
The only guy she saw running
from the scene of
the crime was O'Neill,
and that's the guy
I want to talk to.
There he is! Now, here!
Eddie Lomax.
That verifies Paul
O'Neill's story.
And in any court of
law, he's off the hook.
Thank you very
much, Mrs. Luzinsky.
You're very welcome, Sergeant.
Well, well, if it
weren't for Chris,
we could be done now. Yeah.
But let's see if Eddie
Lomax has ever
had dealings with
our other suspects.
That is, after we
take Sarah here
for a sarsaparilla and
hear a little more about
Lee Arthur Greenway.
Well, that will take a
double vodka martini.
Oh, my...
Next time, we're sitting
where I can smoke.
There won't be a next time.
Good Lord... What?
Oh, yeah.
Judge Franklin, Mr. Brennert.
Your secretary told
me you'd be here.
I told her it was a
matter of life or death.
But since I've got you
both here, this man's
name is Eddie Lomax...
You recognize him?
Can't help you.
He ever work in
one of your factories?
How would I know?
Ask my personnel manager.
Uh-huh.
How about you, Judge?
Did he ever appear
before you? Not
as far as I know.
Ah. Hey, we're trying to have
dinner here, do you mind?
Oh.
Oh... Janice, please
come sit down.
Uh, Mr. Matlock
was just leaving.
Well, perhaps you care
to join us for a drink?
Oh, no thank you.
I have to be going.
I'm sure you all
have a lot to discuss,
so I'll just...
Well, what was he doing here?
Nothing for you to
concern yourself with.
We, uh... we haven't
seen you since
the funeral, Janice.
We were worried about you.
I'm holding up.
Janice, you know
we were Brian's
good friends, and...
so if there's anything
that we can do,
anything that you need...
Thank you. That's very sweet.
Actually, there is
something you can do for me.
I don't know what the
two of you have been up to,
but I'm pretty sure that it
cost my husband his life.
And Joseph Chan his.
I'm also pretty sure that
if I took what I do know
to someone like Ben Matlock,
he just might be able to put it
all together.
So this is what you can
do for me, gentlemen.
You can cut me in.
Mr. Reardon! Here he is!
If you're convicted,
do you think it'll
lead to tighter laws?
How did you plan the
murder? How do you feel
about spending the
rest of your life in prison?
Have you sold your
story to TV? Chris!
What do you think your
chances are of parole?
Get away from me!
Are you crazy?!
Now, you come unglued out there
and you don't have a prayer.
I don't have a prayer anyway.
The whole world's got me tried,
convicted and sentenced.
You lose your temper
with those people,
it's going to be
in the newspaper,
it's going to be on television.
And you're going
to make it real easy
for people to
believe that you are
some kind of raving maniac
who could very well
have shot the mayor.
Now, I'm going to tell you
something: if there's
one thing I hate,
it's losing a case before I
ever walk in the courtroom.
Now, that's going
to be the longest
20 yards you ever walked.
But you got to walk it.
And you got to keep your cool.
You got that?!
Now, turn around and face
that mirror, and
repeat after me.
Here he is!
No comments.
We'll have a statement later.
Excuse us, please.
Mr. Reardon, are you
changing your plea?
Do you think you could
kill somebody again?
Do you own many handguns?
Why'd you do it?
Who'd you vote for
in the last election?
Do you plan to plead insanity?
One more question!
♪ ♪
Look what you just did, pinhead!
Now... Whoa!
Hit him!
Is that it? Is that it?
Sit down. Yes, sir.
That's right, I was
Mayor Barelli's press aid.
It was my job to deal
with the news media.
Not only did I organize
the press conference
that morning,
but I was at
Mayor Barelli's side
when he was shot.
You were standing there,
yes, but did you actually
see the person who
shot him, Miss Landis?
Yes.
As the mayor began his
speech, I-I looked around.
You know, to gauge
people's reactions.
I happened to look
toward the mezzanine,
and I saw someone standing there
pointing a gun right at Brian.
A split second
later, the man fired.
Is that man here in this
courtroom today? Yes.
He's right there.
That's the man who
killed Mayor Barelli!
That's a lie! No, Chris, please!
The defendant will refrain
from making any comments.
This is nuts! Am I really
supposed to sit here
while people lie
about me? This is nuts!
Sit down immediately!
Why the hell
don't you make her tell
the truth?! Your Honor,
Order! if I might just have
a word with my client?
It's a conspiracy! I will
have order! Mr. Matlock...
You're all part of it! Sit down!
Control your client.
Are you or are you not going
to yield to the
authority of this court,
and comport yourself properly
from here on
out? No, I will not!
Yes, yes, yes! I will not! Stop!
I have no choice but
to deal with you the
way I've always dealt
with people like you.
Bailiff!
Prosecution may continue.
Let the record show
that Miss Landis
has identified the
defendant as the man
she saw shoot
Mayor Brian Barelli.
I have no further questions.
Defense wish to cross?
Yes, Your Honor.
Before I cross, I feel compelled
to say that while His Honor
is within his rights,
in over 30 years of practice,
I have never seen
anything to equal this.
Mr. Matlock, I've
dealt with your client.
Don't force me to deal with you.
Of course, Your Honor.
Having made my statement
that in 30 years I've never seen
anything to equal this
and knowing it's on the
record, I will move on.
Mr. Matlock!
With the court's permission,
I would like to re-create
some of the conditions
that existed in the
rotunda that morning.
Theatrics, Mr. Matlock?
Theatrics?
Mr. Matlock...
Your Honor, I need
to make a point here,
and I need these
theatrics to make that point.
Proceed.
Uh, Miss Landis, uh, what's
a press conference like?
It's very hectic.
Reporters running
around all over the place,
cameras, microphones, cables.
Lights?
Oh, yes, you can't have TV
and film coverage without lights.
Let me, let me explain
what I've done here.
I've asked these gentlemen
from the TV station
to come down and set up lights
the way they were at
the rotunda that morning.
Now, uh, you were by the mayor
while he was making his speech,
so let's pretend he's
making his speech, all right?
All right.
Now, the lights were
on you as they are now...
Uh, well... Approximately.
You had about this
much light on you.
Well, yes, I guess it
was about this much.
Of course, uh... conditions
are not exactly as they were
in the rotunda that morning.
The man you saw
fire the shot was
much farther away
from you than I am now.
And you had to look
above the lights rather than
below them, is that right?
Uh, yes. Yes, that's right.
But you can still see me?
Yes.
Can you see me well
enough to point to me?
Sure.
Give me a good strong point.
You didn't really
get a good look
at the man who fired
the shot, did you?
No.
You saw someone
dressed like Chris Reardon.
And in your desire to
see someone punished
for bringing
Brian Barelli's life
to such a sudden and tragic end,
you rushed to a
judgment, didn't you?
Yes.
I'm sorry.
Thank you.
Nothing further.
Hiya. Uh, my
name's Paul O'Neill.
Listen, there's a guy
in the bar over there
who's wanted for questioning
in a murder
investigation in Illinois.
The hell you say? Who?
Eddie Lomax.
I find that kind
of hard to believe.
Eddie, uh... I've
known Eddie for years.
Catching his fair share
of scraps but, uh, murder?
Are you a cop?
No.
You got a writ of extradition?
I thought you might call.
I'm afraid I can't do that.
Not on your word.
You can't just let him go free.
Until he breaks a
law in my jurisdiction,
I sure as hell can.
Hi. Brenda, isn't it?
You know you almost got me
fired the last time you were here,
did you know that,
Mr. Matlock? Oh, I'm sorry,
but you must be doing
something right, if you're still here.
Mr. Brennert is busy.
I just want to ask him
a couple questions
about Judge Franklin.
Where the hell did he go?!
When I see him, I'll ask him.
♪ ♪
Howdy.
Hey.
You remember me?
What the hell are
you doing here?
Well, I just wanted
to thank you.
You know, for cracking
my head open in that alley,
stealing my gun,
framing me for Chan's
murder, shooting Mayor Barelli.
Actually, uh... I'm
doing a poll of killers
and I thought I
should start with you.
What did you call me?
A murderer. You should
be sent to the chair.
That's gotta hurt.
I'm gonna rip your heart out.
Oh, it's about time.
Arrest this man...
Assault and battery.
Hey, it was self-defense.
He hit me first.
Come on... who do
you think hit whom?
Coming! I'm coming!
Mr. Montero?
Yeah.
Good morning. Here's your paper.
Interesting article
on page two about that warehouse
that blew up a couple days ago.
Who are you?
My name's Ben
Matlock. I'm a lawyer.
I went to see your boss
Jack Brennert the other day,
but he didn't want to
see me, so he slipped out.
But my associate followed him.
And guess what?
What?
My associate saw him
slip you an attaché case.
He figured there was
some money in it...
A payoff or something,
so he followed you.
He did what?
Yeah.
Followed you to that warehouse,
watched you put the
attaché case down on a desk,
and then watched you leave.
And then you know what happened?
Damn thing blew up.
Big explosion.
Startled Tyler.
So what do you want?
I want you in court today.
Forget it.
Get your foot out of my
door before I call the cops.
Please, call 'em.
I'll show them this subpoena...
They'll put your heinie in
the back seat of that patrol car
and you'll be in court.
Ready?
Yeah.
Mr. Brennert, you have
widespread real estate holdings
in Chicago, don't you?
That's true.
According to the official deed
recorded at the courthouse,
you have purchased
ten... uh, industrial parcels
in the last six
months, is that right?
Quite true.
Why all this rush to buy
West Side industrial properties?
Real estate
speculation, Mr., Matlock.
By low, sell high.
It's very simple.
You wouldn't by any chance
be pressuring these businessmen
into selling would you?
I always offer a
high market value.
Huh.
And this, uh, rash of fires
on the West Side recently,
you wouldn't know anything
about that, would you?
In business,
you take advantage
of the breaks.
Or make your own.
Now, what is that,
an accusation?
Your Honor, I have
subpoenaed another witness
to testify this morning
and I'd like him removed
from the courtroom at this time,
so that he won't be
influenced by anything
Mr. Brennert may or may not say.
Very well.
Where is this witness?
He's right back there.
Mr. Thomas Montero.
Bailiff.
Tom Montero works
for you, doesn't he?
Yes.
He's an arsonist, isn't he?
Objection! Relevancy,
no foundation.
He torches building
so that you can go in
later and buy 'em up
cheaply, doesn't he?
That's a lie.
Objection! Relevancy!
Mr. Matlock...
Your Honor, in a moment,
I'll show relevancy.
Proceed.
Now, Mr. Brennert,
the penalty for perjury
in this state is severe, so
I'm going to give you a chance
to reconsider your testimony.
And I remind you
that Mr. Montero is
just outside that door.
Now we'll get the
truth out of you,
or we'll get it out of him.
Now did you or did
you not provide him
with incendiary devices
that he used to burn
one or more buildings
on the West Side?
I did not.
And if he says
I did, he's a liar.
Why did you want those
properties so badly?
Just tell us.
Read my lips, will ya?
Real estate speculation.
Speculation.
That's when you buy
property without knowing
whether its value
will go up or down.
But you knew, didn't you?
And I know something, too.
You're not going to
get away with this.
I'm gonna break your heart.
There was no real
speculation, was there?
You had inside information
from Mayor Barelli.
Which properties
on the West Side
would be condemned by the city
for the purpose of building
the new inner city
expressway, didn't you?
Yes, it's true, but I
didn't kill anybody.
One thing at a time.
You knew the route
of the expressway?
Yes, I did.
And that's why
you were so anxious
to get those properties,
because you knew the city would
then have to buy them from you.
That's right.
And the mayor found out
about what you were doing,
and that's when he
accused you of betraying him,
and that's why
he had to be killed.
I didn't kill anybody.
Stuart Franklin
and Janice Barelli...
They were my partners.
Don't ask me who
killed Brian, ask them.
Maybe I will.
Uh, a moment, Your Honor.
Eddie Lomax is
now in the custody
of the Chicago
police department.
Uh, Your Honor, may
counsel approach the bench?
Mr. Price.
You must have really given
them an earful, huh, Chris?
Your Honor, I'd like to
request an adjournment
until tomorrow morning.
I need time to interview a
new and possibly vital witness.
Who hired you to
kill Joseph Chan?
I don't know what
you're talking about.
The same person who
hired you to kill Mayor Barelli?
I still don't know what
you're talking about.
We can place you at
Joseph Chan's murder.
Big deal.
A smart man
would make it easy
on himself, Eddie.
This is boring.
And I'm missing dinner.
So, when you've got something...
you give me a call.
Guard.
Hello, Eddie.
Jimmy.
What's going on?
Nothing much.
You're the one
killed Eddie Lomax?
It was self-defense.
Tell me what happened.
They put me in a cell with him.
Next thing I know, he's
starting to swing at me.
So I duck... he keeps
coming after me.
So, I, uh, I swing at him.
Only I connect.
Then I see he's got
a shiv in his hand.
He comes at me.
I grab it.
He knocks me around.
We roll around
the floor wrestling,
and, uh... the next
thing I know, it's, uh,
sticking out of his chest.
He started it? You bet.
Did you know one another?
Never saw him before in my life.
Stand up.
Eddie's right hand was
broken in two places.
His arm was in a sling.
But he started a fight
with a total stranger
who was a foot taller and
50 pounds heavier than him,
is that it?
That's what happened.
There's nothing in
here on Jimmy Dolan.
Mm. And so much for the
clippings on Jack Brennert.
Eh, now what?
I don't know.
But I am starving.
You know, it's taken
everything I have
not to make a pass at you.
I'll take that as a compliment.
Maybe you'll stick
around after the case?
That could be tomorrow,
if we don't find something.
Hey, look at this.
What is it?
Jimmy Dolan's rap sheet.
That's a lot of arrests.
37. There's no convictions.
Doesn't even look like
he's ever been to trial.
Tell you anything?
Your Honor, before we begin
and before the jury enters,
my client would like to make
a brief personal statement.
Very well.
Bailiff?
I'm sorry I behaved
so disrespectfully.
It's something I regret,
and it won't happen again.
Bailiff, remove the restraints,
and then bring in the jury.
I hope that wasn't just a speech
your attorneys had you
memorize, Mr. Reardon.
If you disrupt these
proceedings again,
I'll throw all of you in
jail for contempt of court.
Yes, sir.
At this time, defense
would like to call...
Judge Stuart
Franklin to the stand.
I understand you
and Mayor Barelli
were old friends.
His ghetto was across
the alley from mine.
We grew up together.
Did you go to school together?
Uh, through high school,
and then he went on to college
and I joined the police force.
And that gave
you the opportunity
to go to night school and
eventually earn a law degree.
That's correct.
You're a real bootstrapped
man, Judge Franklin.
Voters like that.
It's no wonder that you
were elected to the city council
by such a landslide.
And Brian Barelli was on the
council with you, wasn't he?
Yes, he was.
Two old friends
serving side by side.
Must've been quite a shock
when he stabbed you in the back.
He did no such thing.
But, Judge Franklin,
it's-it's common knowledge
that Brian Barelli convinced you
to take the judgeship
which you now hold.
And with you out of the running,
the leaders of the
political party at the time
turned to him as the candidate.
That's warmed-over,
backroom gossip.
He destroyed your chances
of ever being mayor of this city,
and you never
forgave him, did you?
That is not true.
Oh, I know you said
over and over again,
what old and dear
friends you were.
And, uh, you didn't hesitate
to use that friendship, did you?
For inside information.
Information that
could do two things:
make you a lot of money,
and maybe, somewhere
down the line,
destroy the political
career of your old friend.
What you've said is not true.
Do you deny...
that... you were a
member of a plan
to buy up industrial
West Side property?
The only property
I own in this city
is my home. Judge Franklin,
as a jurist, you know full well
you did not answer my question.
And you, sir, have not
introduced any evidence
to prove I was a member
of this conspiracy.
A simple yes or no will do.
Were you a member
of a conspiracy
to purchase West Side property?
No, I was not. But you did know
of the plan the city
had to build a new road.
Of course.
And you discussed
the route with the mayor.
I may have; I don't recall.
I fail to see the point
of all this, Your Honor.
Your Honor, I'll make
the point right now.
Please do.
Immediately. Thanks. Mm-hmm.
Please tell the
court what this is.
A check.
Made out in what amount?
$150,000.
Made out to whom?
Janice Barelli.
Made up by whom?
Me.
Yeah. Yeah.
Now, you may wonder what
I'm doing with this check.
Well, I'll tell you.
Janice Barelli gave it to me...
right after she convinced you
that a three-way conspiracy
would be better
than going to jail.
'Cause, you see, she was
actually conspiring with me.
You remember that,
uh, meeting you had
in that fancy restaurant?
If you don't, I'm sure she'll
come up here on the stand
and remind you.
I remember it.
So... you do not deny...
you were a member of
Mr. Brennert's scheme.
No.
Actually,
it was Joseph Chan's
scheme, wasn't it?
He came to you first.
He needed you...
to help persuade the
mayor the new expressway
should go through
the industrial section
of the West Side, rather than
through the predominantly
black residential section
on the South Side.
At least...
that's what you
told Mrs. Barelli.
Yes, but none of this has
anything whatsoever to do
with the matter
before this court,
which is whether or not
your client is guilty of murder.
I have to concur, Your Honor.
This line of questioning
is irrational and distracting.
Uh, Your Honor, may I just
take a different approach?
Proceed. Thank you.
Do you know a fella
named Eddie Lomax?
Only through conversations
I've had with you.
The police extradited him
from Texas to charge him
with Joseph Chan's murder
and to question him
about the mayor's murder.
And knowing how fast news
travels around the courthouse,
I figured you had heard
about it. Mr. Matlock,
I am too busy to
listen to gossip.
All right, let's forget
about Eddie Lomax
for the moment.
Do you know who Jimmy Dolan is?
I'm sorry, I've
never heard of him.
Before you were a judge,
before you were
on the city council,
a public defender,
you were a what?
A police officer.
And back when you
were a police officer,
there was a young man
named Jimmy Dolan...
who was arrested on
crimes ranging from assault
to grand theft,
37 times, and
never went to trial.
Never prosecuted.
Now do you remember?
No.
Well, let me read you...
what some of the
arresting officers
had to say back then.
This one, uh, is by
Detective Ted Withers.
May 17, 1974.
"Released Jimmy Dolan,
dropped grand theft auto charge
at Stuart Franklin's request."
Detective Sergeant Arthur
Weingarten, November 14,
1976.
"Surefire case against
Jimmy Dolan dropped,
re: Sergeant Stuart Franklin."
Sergeant Stuart Franklin.
That was you, wasn't it?
Yes.
Jimmy Dolan was
your snitch, wasn't he?
Yes.
He did favors for you,
you did favors for him.
It was so long ago.
He recruited Eddie
Lomax for you, didn't he?
No. Mayor Barelli was about
to expose you as
the Judas you are,
not only for betraying him,
but for betraying members
of the black community
who would have benefited
had that expressway been
built through their district.
So you had Jimmy Dolan
hire someone to
assassinate the mayor
and Joseph Chan, didn't he? No!
And that man was
Eddie Lomax. None of this
is true! Once the police
got hold of Eddie Lomax,
you asked Jimmy Dolan
to do one last favor for you,
didn't you? No.
You had him stab
Eddie Lomax to
death in his cell.
That's right.
Eddie Lomax is dead...
and he was killed...
by a man... who was
hired... by this man.
Coincidence.
It's mere coincidence!
You have not proved one thing.
Maybe not.
And I don't really have to.
But I'm pretty sure I
have demonstrated
that someone other
than my client had
a damn good reason
to kill Mayor Barelli.
That someone
hired... someone else...
to actually commit the crime,
so the first someone
might escape detection.
As far as my client's concerned,
it's called...
"reasonable doubt."
And so far as proof,
I met Jimmy Dolan.
Tall drink of water.
And I'm sure, when
the good officers
of the Chicago police
department talk with him for awhile,
he'll get a little shorter.
Nothing further.
We, the jury, find the
defendant not guilty.
Thank you, ladies and gentlemen.
This court is adjourned.
Pretty good system, huh?
Better than I thought.
Thank you. Okay.
- Congratulations.
- Hey, listen,
if you ever find yourself
in this situation again,
don't yell at the judge.
See ya.
Dinner tonight?
Oh... I have to pack.
Oh.
I have a story to write.
Oh...
Well.
Well what?
I owe you title to my house.
Oh.
Well, that's okay.
It's probably somewhere I
wouldn't want to live, anyway.
www.tvsubtitles.net